<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="codegenarchitecture">
  <title>Code generation architecture</title>

  <para>The code generation mechanism in the <property>Hibernate Tools</property> consists of a few
    core concepts. This section explains their overall structure which are the same for the Ant and
    Eclipse tools.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Hibernate Meta Model</title>

    <para>The meta model is the model used by Hibernate Core to perform its object relational
      mapping. The model includes information about tables, columns, classes, properties,
      components, values, collections etc. The API is in <literal>org.hibernate.mapping</literal>
      and its main entry point is the <property>Configuration</property> class, the same class that is
      used to build a session factory.</para>

    <para>The model represented by the <property>Configuration</property> class can be build in many
      ways. The following list the currently supported ones in <property>Hibernate Tools</property>. </para>

    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A Core configuration uses Hibernate Core and supports reading <emphasis>
              <property>hbm.xml</property>
            </emphasis> files, requires a <emphasis>
              <property>hibernate.cfg.xml</property>
            </emphasis>. Named core in Eclipse and 
             <code>&lt;configuration&gt;</code>
               in ant.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>An Annotation configuration uses Hibernate Annotations and supports <emphasis>
              <property>hbm.xml</property>
            </emphasis> and annotated classes, requires a <emphasis>
              <property>hibernate.cfg.xml</property>
            </emphasis>. Named annotations in Eclipse and 
            <code>&lt;annotationconfiguration&gt;</code>
             in ant.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A JPA configuration uses a Hibernate EntityManager and supports <emphasis>
              <property>hbm.xml</property>
            </emphasis> and annotated classes requires that the project has a <emphasis>
              <property>META-INF/persistence.xml</property>
            </emphasis> in its classpath. Named JPA in Eclipse and 
             <code>&lt;jpaconfiguration&gt;</code>
              in ant.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A JDBC configuration uses <property>Hibernate Tools</property> reverse engineering
            and reads its mappings via JDBC metadata + additional reverse engineering files
            (reveng.xml). Automatically used in Eclipse when doing reverse engineering from JDBC and
            named 
                <code>&lt;jdbcconfiguration&gt;</code>
               in ant.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>In most projects you will normally use only one of the Core, Annotation or JPA
      configuration and possibly the JDBC configuration if you are using the reverse engineering
      facilities of <property>Hibernate Tools</property>. </para>

    <note>
      <title>Note:</title>
      <para>No matter which Hibernate Configuration type you are using <property>Hibernate
        Tools</property> supports them.</para>
    </note>

    <para>The following drawing illustrates the core concepts:</para>

    <para>
      <figure>
        <title>Hibernate Core Concepts</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="images/code_generation/code_generation_1.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="html">

            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/code_generation/code_generation_1.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>

    <para>The code generation is done based on the Configuration model no matter which type of
      configuration have been used to create the meta model, and thus the code generation is
      independent on the source of the meta model and represented via Exporters.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Exporters</title>

    <para>Code generation is done in so called Exporters. An <code>Exporter</code> is handed a
      Hibernate Meta Model represented as a <code>Configuration</code> instance and it is then
      the job of the exporter to generate a set of code artifacts.</para>

    <para>The tools provides a default set of Exporter's which can be used in both Ant and the
      Eclipse UI. Documentation for these Exporters is in the <link linkend="ant">Ant Tools</link>
      and <link linkend="plugins">Eclipse Plugins</link> chapters.</para>

    <para>Users can provide their own customer Exporter's, either by custom classes implementing the
      Exporter interface or simply be providing custom templates. This is documented at <xref
        linkend="hbmtemplate"/></para>
  </section>
</chapter>
