<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="setup">
  <title>Download and install Hibernate Tools</title>

  <para><property>Hibernate Tools</property> can be used &quot;standalone&quot; via Ant
    1.6.x or fully integrated into an Eclipse 3.3.x + WTP 2.x based IDE, such as <property>JBoss
      Tools</property> or a default Eclipse 3.3.x + WTP 2.x installation. The following describes
    the install steps in these environments.</para>

  <section>
    <title>JBoss Tools</title>

    <para><property>JBoss Tools 2.x</property> includes <property>Hibernate Tools</property> and
      thus nothing is required besides <ulink url="http://labs.jboss.com/tools/download/index.html"
        >downloading</ulink> and <ulink
        url="http://www.redhat.com/developer_studio/guides/GettingStartedGuide/html_single/#JBossToolsInstall"
        >installing JBoss Tools</ulink>. If you need to update to a newer version of the
        <property>Hibernate Tools</property> just follow the instructions in the Eclipse IDE
      section.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Eclipse IDE</title>

    <para>To install into any <property>Eclipse 3.3.x</property> based Eclipse IDE you can either
      download the <property>Hibernate Tools</property> distribution from the <ulink
        url="http://www.hibernate.org/6.html">Hibernate website</ulink> or use the <ulink
        url="http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/updates/stable/">JBoss Tools Update Site</ulink>
      (see also <ulink url="http://tools.hibernate.org">http://tools.hibernate.org</ulink> for links
      to the update site).</para>

    <para>If you download the <property>Hibernate Tools</property> distribution you need to place
      the <emphasis>
        <property>/plugins</property>
      </emphasis> and <emphasis>
        <property>/feature</property>
      </emphasis> directory into your eclipse directory or eclipse extensions directory. Sometimes
      Eclipse does not automatically detect new plugins and thus the tools will not be activated. To
      ensure eclipse sees these changes run eclipse with the -clean option. E.g. <literal>eclipse
        -clean</literal> Using the updatesite does not require any additional steps.</para>

    <note>
      <para>If you need more basic instructions on installing plugins and general usage of eclipse
        then check out <ulink url="https://eclipse-tutorial.dev.java.net/"
          >https://eclipse-tutorial.dev.java.net/</ulink> and especially <ulink
          url="https://eclipse-tutorial.dev.java.net/visual-tutorials/updatemanager.html"
          >https://eclipse-tutorial.dev.java.net/visual-tutorials/updatemanager.html</ulink> which
        covers using the update manager.</para>
    </note>

    <section>
      <title>Usage of Eclipse WTP</title>

      <para>The <property>Hibernate Tools</property> plugins currently use <property>WTP
        2.x</property> which at this time is the latest stable release from the Eclipse Webtools
        project.</para>

      <para>Because the WTP project not always have had proper versioning of their plugins there
        might exist WTP plugins in your existing eclipse directory from other Eclipse based projects
        that are from an earlier WTP release but has either the same version number or higher. It is
        thus recommended that if you have issues with WTP provided features to try and install the
        plugins on a clean install of eclipse to ensure there are no version collisions.</para>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Ant</title>

    <para>To use the tools via Ant you need the <emphasis>
        <property>hibernate-tools.jar</property>
      </emphasis> and associated libraries. The libraries are included in the distribution from the
      Hibernate website and the Eclipse updatesite. The libraries are located in the eclipse plugins
      directory at <emphasis>
        <property>/plugins/org.hibernate.eclipse.x.x.x/lib/tools/</property></emphasis>. These libraries are 100%
      independent from the eclipse platform. How to use these via ant tasks are described in the
        <link linkend="ant">Ant Tools</link> chapter.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
