<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="setup">
  <title>Download and install Hibernate Tools</title>

  <para>Hibernate tools can be used "standalone" via Ant 1.6.x or fully
  integrated into a Eclipse 3.3.x + WTP 2.x based IDE, such as JBoss Tools or an
  default Eclipse 3.3.x + WTP 2.x installation. The following describes the install
  steps in these environments.</para>

  <section>
    <title>JBoss Tools</title>

    <para>JBoss Tools 2.x includes Hibernate Tools and thus nothing is
    required besides downloading and installing JBoss Tools. If you need
    to update to a newer version of the Hibernate Tools just follow the
    instructions in the Eclipse IDE section.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Eclipse IDE</title>

    <para>To install into any Eclipse 3.3.x based Eclipse IDE you can either
    download the Hibernate Tools distribution from the Hibernate website or
    use the JBoss Tools update site (see http://tools.hibernate.org for 
    links to the update site).</para>

    <para>If you download the Hibernate Tools distribution you need to place
    the /plugins and /feature directory into your eclipse directory or eclipse
    extensions directory. Sometimes Eclipse does not automatically detect new
    plugins and thus the tools will not be activated. To ensure eclipse sees
    these changes run eclipse with the -clean option. E.g. <literal>eclipse
    -clean</literal> Using the updatesite does not require any additional
    steps.</para>

    <para>Tip: If you need more basic instructions on installing plugins and
    general usage of eclipse then check out
    https://eclipse-tutorial.dev.java.net/ and especially
    https://eclipse-tutorial.dev.java.net/visual-tutorials/updatemanager.html
    which covers using the update manager.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Usage of Eclipse WTP</title>

      <para>The Hibernate tools plugins currently uses WTP 2.x which at this
      time is the latest stable release from the Eclipse Webtools
      project.</para>

      <para>Because the WTP project not always have had proper versioning of their plugins
      there might exist WTP plugins in your existing eclipse directory from
      other Eclipse based projects that are from an earlier WTP release but
      has either the same version number or higher. It is thus recommended
      that if you have issues with WTP provided features to try and install
      the plugins on a clean install of eclipse to ensure there are no
      version collisions.</para>
      
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Ant</title>

    <para>To use the tools via Ant you need the hibernate-tools.jar and
    associated libraries. The libraries are included in the distribution from
    the Hibernate website and the Eclipse updatesite. The libraries are
    located in the eclipse plugins directory at
    <literal>/plugins/org.hibernate.eclipse.x.x.x/lib/tools/.</literal>These
    libraries are 100% independent from the eclipse platform. How to use these
    via ant tasks are described in the Ant chapter.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>