<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="introduction">

	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>
		<property>Hibernate Tools</property> is a collection of tools for <ulink url="http://www.hibernate.org/">Hibernate 3</ulink> and related projects. The tools provide Ant
        tasks and Eclipse plugins for performing reverse engineering, code generation, visualization
        and interaction with Hibernate.</para>

	<section id="hibernate_key_features">
		<title>Key Features</title>

		<para>The table below lists the key features found in <property>Hibernate Tools</property>.</para>

		<table>
			<title>Key Functionality for Hibernate Tools</title>
			<tgroup cols="3">

				<colspec colnum="1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colnum="2" colwidth="5*"/>
				<colspec colnum="3" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>

				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Feature</entry>
						<entry>Benefit</entry>
						<entry>Chapter</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>

				<tbody>

					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>Code Generation through Ant Task</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>
								Allows to generate mapping or Java code through reverse engineering, schema generation and generation of other artifacts during the build process.
							</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<xref linkend="ant"/>
						</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>Wizards for creation purposes and code generation</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>
								A set of wizards are provided with the <productname>Hibernate Eclipse Tools</productname> to quickly create common <productname>Hibernate</productname> files such as configuration (<filename>cfg.xml</filename>) files, mapping files and <filename>reveng.xml</filename> as well. The Code Generation wizard helps by generating a series of various artifacts, and there is even support for completely reverse engineering an existing database schema.
							</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<xref linkend="map_file_wizard"/>
							<xref linkend="hib_config_file"/>
							<xref linkend="code_gen"/>
						</entry>
					</row>


					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>Mapping and Configuration files Editors</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>
								Support auto-completion and syntax highlighting. Editors also support semantic auto-completion for class names and property/field names, making it much more versatile than a normal XML editor.
							</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<xref linkend="map_config_editor"/>
						</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>Tools for organizing and controlling Reverse Engineering</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>
								The Code Generation wizard provides powerful functionality for generating a series of various artifacts such as domain model classes, mapping files, and annotated EJB3 entity beans, and the <filename>reveng.xml</filename> file editor provides control over this processes.
							</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<xref linkend="code_gen"/>
							<xref linkend="rev_xml_editor"/>
						</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>Hibernate Console</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>
								It is a new perspective in Eclipse which provides an overview of your Hibernate Console configurations, and were you also can get an interactive view of your persistent classes and their relationships. The console allows you to execute HQL queries against your database and browse the result directly in Eclipse.
							</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<xref linkend="hib_console"/>
						</entry>
					</row>
                	
					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>HQL Editor and Hibernate Criteria Editor</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>
								The editors are provided for writing, editing and executing HQL queries and criterias. They also have the ability to generate simple queries.
							</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<xref linkend="hql_and_criteria_editors"/>
						</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>Functional Mapping Diagram</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>Makes possible to visualize the structure of entities and the relationships between them.</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<xref linkend="map_diagram"/>
						</entry>
					</row>


					<row>
						<entry>
							<para>Eclipse JDT integration</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>
								<productname>Hibernate Tools</productname> integrates into the Java code completion and build support for Java in Eclipse. This gives you HQL code completion inside Java code. Additionally, <productname>Hibernate Tools</productname> will display problem markers if your queries are not valid against the console configuration associated with the project.
							</para>
						</entry>
					</row>

				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Other relevant resources on the topic</title>
        
    <para>The <productname>Hibernate Tools</productname> page on <ulink url="http://www.hibernate.org/subprojects/tools.html">hibernate.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para>
			All <productname>JBDS</productname> release documentation can be found on the <ulink url="http://docs.redhat.com/docs/en-US/JBoss_Developer_Studio/index.html">RedHat Documentation</ulink> website.
		</para>
		<para>
			There is some additional information on <productname>Hibernate</productname> on the <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/community/wiki/JBossHibernate3">JBoss Wiki</ulink> page. 
		</para>
		<para>
			Nightly documentation builds are available <ulink url="http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/nightly-docs/">here</ulink>.
		</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
